{
  "reference_number": "1630",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "This should be seen as an ongoing process, the net zero emissions target by 2050 as per the Paris Accord should be seen as a\n\n starting point. The technologies, practices and policies that get us to the 2050 target should be continued to maintain a sustainable\n long term program where human societies continue to reduce their impact on the environment."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "We must target all our emissions across all industries so that we maintain an incentive for innovation and improvement in all sectors\n\n of our economy. We already know that change in stock feed (kelp added to diet, increased plantain in pasture) can reduce methane\n emissions from cattle hence it is imperative that we provide an incentive mechanism to take up new practices and maintain leading\n edge research across our agricultural and energy industries. We must also consider that methane is not just a short term green\n\n house gas as the final stage of break down of methane results in CO2 being formed from the carbon atom."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We need to become self responsible and self contained as a country to meet our zero carbon targets and fully embed a culture of\n sustainability within New Zealand. International trading schemes for carbon credits can make it too easy for cash rich bad\n environmental players to avoid taking necessary and practical direct actions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Downwards only. We need to get real bout the necessity of meeting these targets and need leave loop holes for future less\n environmentally aware governments to make excuses for not maintaining New Zealands obligations"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Agree that this is a practical framework. There should be some boundaries set to how far targets can be moved ie an operational\n\n envelope within which each 5 year target can be adjusted."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "There should be some boundaries set to how far targets can be moved ie an operational envelope within which the third budget\nmaybe able to be adjusted without jeopardising New Zealands obligation to meet the 2050 target. We must ensure that operational\n\nadjustments can't be used as a way of simply deferring actions until it is too late. I would expect some sor tof mechanism so that if\nthe targets for one 5 year period are reduced, then the operating envelope for subsequent periods is shifted to enforce the\n\ngovernment to stay on track for subsequent emissions budgets and prevent a succession of weak targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Need to set very clear definitions around \"exceptional circumstances\", limits on how much the budget maybe varied (say only by 5%\nand consider that any reduction in the 2nd 5 year period be added onto the 3rd 5 year period so that the current 15 year target is\nmaintained."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is essential for maintaining accountability that time frames be clearly defined for setting plans, setting emissions budgets and\n\nresponding to recommendations from the proposed Climate Change Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Need to ensure that plans and budgets are well thought out so that they drive the right behaviours in all affected industiores and\nacross society. ie. targets need to drive behaviour towards sustainable practices and sustainable ways of living, not just to achieving a\n\nmeans of compliance."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support an advisory and monitoring role however the legislation also needs to clearly define the governments obligations to respond\nto that advice."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This can work either way however there should be an obligation to consult. ie. if set by government, then the government should\n\nhave an obligation to consult with the Climate Change Commission before making changes, similalry, if set by the Climate Change\nCommission, then should be obligated to conult with government before make changes."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "In addition, some work needs to be done on establishing clearly defined and accurate means to measure our progress. The Climate\n\nChange Commission will need access to experts that maintain and updated the measuring systems to ensure consistency of\nreporting and that our reporting systems are using best practice and being updated when required to use new and emerging\ntechnology."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "To achieve our zero carbon targets we need a culture change within New Zealand. Shifting our culture and adapting to both climate\nchanges and a new way of living as required to support a carbon neutral economy has to be an integral part of the Zero Carbon Bill if\n\nit is to succeed."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There are clear advantages in doing this. Also need to ensure that a consistent approach to risk identification and management is\n\nbeing applied across the country. Believe there needs to be a more centralized resource pool to provide tools and methodologies to\nother organizations/councils etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Planting trees is a clear part of reaching our zero carbon target. We need to ensure that we are planting trees that are of long term\necological benefit to the region in which they are planted. Forestry is likely to be a part of this equation but should only be a part due\n\nto negative ecological impact of forestry in some areas (effects of monoculture on biodiversity, runoff and environmental damage\nduring harvesting, loss of carbon sink between harvesting and replanting."
    }
  ]
}
